

Ege Ulgen MD, PhD

November 2023

Genomics England Limited



he/him

+44 7796 427839

Ege.Ulgen@genomicsengland. co.uk

egeulgen

ege-ulgen

# About me ———

MD-PhD professional in bioinformatics with a medical degree from Acibadem University in 2015, postdoctoral experience at Yale University in 2016, followed by a PhD in Biostatistics and Bioinformatics in 2022. Currently a Bioinformatics Engineer at Genomics England, where I focus on creating and enhancing software for the cancer genomic medicine service.

### Education

2016-2022 Ph.D., Biostatistics and Bioinformatics

**Acibadem University** 

2009-2015 M.D., summa cum laude

Acibadem University

Worked

# Experience

2023-Bioinformatics Engineer Developing features for and maintaining software

for the cancer genomic medicine service.

Genomics England

2021-2023 Lecturer Worked as a lecturer for the undergrad and grad courses on

biostatistics and bioinformatics topics.

Acibadem University

2018-2023 Bioinformatics Specialist

on developing and maintaining multiple whole exome sequencing-based analysis pipelines (cancer and rare disease applications) for the Istanbul-based medical

diagnostics company.

Epigenetiks

2016 Postdoctoral Associate Briefly worked as a post-doc

associate at the Gunel Lab, Yale School of Medicine, where I had previously done multiple internships between 2011-2014. Research in neurogenetics, particularly malformations of cortical development and brain tumours, performing functional in-vitro analyses to investigate the effect of a SNP in the pathogenesis of gliomas.

Yale University

2015-2023 **Bioinformatics Consultant** Developed and maintained

> the Whole Exome Sequencing pipeline for the local medical diagnostics company based in Istanbul-Turkey. The pipeline allows for the identification of clinicallyrelevant genomics findings in brain tumours, especially regarding gliomas

NeuroOncology Technologies

2012-Research Group Member Participate in

> research on brain tumours, particularly on gliomas. I assist in biostatistical as well as bioinformatics analyses, focusing on the integration of molecular biological and clinical data to improve diagnosis, prognosis and treatment of glioma.

ACU Brain tumour Research Group

# Skills

#### Programming

Python R bash Development

docker

qit

GitLab CI/CD

GitHub Actions

Workflow Management

nextflow

snakemake

# Strengths

Curiosity Proactively seeks innovative solutions.

Time Management Effectively prioritizes tasks, ensuring timely completion of milestones.

Quick Learner

Adapts to new challenges swiftly.

2.3.0	pathfindR.	pathfindR. Enrichment Analysis Utilizing Active Subnetworks				
1.0.1	PANACEA.	Personalized	Network-Based	Anti-Cancer	Therapy	
	Evaluation					

0.4.1 driveR. Prioritizing Cancer Driver Genes Using Genomics Data

2.0.0 pathfindR.data. Data Package for 'pathfindR'

tion
Certificate in Machine Learning. Grade: 94.8% – coursera.org/verify/7QETTCDWHXHP
Certificate in Finding Hidden Messages in DNA (Bioinformatics I) (with Honors). Grade: 96.0% – cours-
era.org/verify/B5Y2QZ4AWTCL Certificate in Genome Sequencing (Bioinformatics II) (with Honors). Grade: 99.0% – coursera.org/verify/242DMGMNGFXA
Certificate in Comparing Genes, Proteins, and Genomes (Bioinformatics III) (with Honors). Grade: 100% – cours-
era.org/verify/N3B77QC9N7V6 Certificate in Molecular Evolution (Bioinformatics IV) (with Honors). Grade: 100% – coursera.org/verify/TM3MWQPRPS47
Certificate in Genomic Data Science and Clustering (Bioinformatics V) (with Honors). Grade: 94.0% – cours-
era.org/verify/AGX8F2V8PU3G Certificate in Bioinformatics Capstone: Big Data in Biology. Grade: 100% – coursera.org/verify/9AKDLPVN9M2U
Certificate in Bioinformatics Specialization. coursera.org/verify/35KWGTCVTJX8

### [Publications]

- Kaya, D., Ülgen, E., Kocagöz, A., & Sezerman, O. (2023). A comparison of various feature extraction and machine learning methods for antimicrobial resistance prediction in streptococcus pneumoniae. Frontiers in
- 2. Ulgen, E., Ozisik, O., & Sezerman, O. (2023). PANACEA: Network-based methods for pharmacotherapy prioritization in personalized oncology. Bioinformatics.
- 3. Levi, C., Uçal, Y., Planchon, S., Ülgen, E., Kumru, P., Ulutaş, P., Sezerman, U., & .... (2023). Proteome analysis of human and goat colostrum: A closer look at whey fractions. Acibadem Saglik Bilimleri Dergisi.
- Cansu, A., Yasemin, U., Planchon, S., Ülgen, E., KUMRU, P., ULUTAŞ, P., & 4. .... (2023). Proteome analysis of human and goat colostrum: A closer look at whey fractions. Acıbadem Üniversitesi Sağlık Bilimleri Dergisi.
- 5. Dogan, B., Gumusoglu, E., Ulgen, E., Sezerman, O., & Gunel, T. (2022). Integrated bioinformatics analysis of validated and circulating miRNAs in ovarian cancer. Genomics & Informatics.
- 6. Keleş, I., Günel, T., Özgör, B., Ülgen, E., Gümüşoğlu, E., Hosseini, M., & .... (2022). Gene pathway analysis of the endometrium at the start of the window of implantation in women with unexplained infertility and unexplained recurrent pregnancy loss: Is .... Human Fertility.
- 7. Yousef, M., Ülgen, E., & Sezerman, O. (2021). CogNet: Classification of gene expression data based on ranked active-subnetwork-oriented KEGG pathway enrichment analysis. PeerJ Computer Science.
- Ülgen, E., & Sezerman, O. (2021). driveR: A novel method for prioritizing 8. cancer driver genes using somatic genomics data. BMC Bioinformatics.
- 9. Albayrak, İ., Azhari, F., Çolak, E., Balcı, B., Ülgen, E., Sezerman, U., Baştu, E., & .... (2021). Endometrial gene expression profiling of recurrent implantation failure after in vitro fertilization. Molecular Biology Reports.
- 10. Ülgen, E., Aras, F., Coşgun, E., Erşen-Danyeli, A., Dinçer, A., Usseli, M., & .... (2021). Correlation of anatomical involvement patterns of insular gliomas with subnetworks of the limbic system. Journal of Neurosurgery.
- 11. Ülgen, E., Can, Ö., Bilguvar, K., Boylu, C. A., Yüksel, Ş. K., & .... (2021). Sequential filtering for clinically relevant variants as a method for clinical interpretation of whole exome sequencing findings in glioma. BMC Medical Genomics.

- 12. Everest, E., Ülgen, E., Uygunoglu, U., Tutuncu, M., Saip, S., Sezerman, O., & .... (2021). Investigation of multiple sclerosis-related pathways through the integration of genomic and proteomic data. *PeerJ*.
- 13. Keleş, I., Ülgen, E., Erkan, M., Çelik, S., Aydın, Y., Önem, A., Kandemir, H., & .... (2020). Comparison of endometrial prostanoid profiles in three infertile subgroups: The missing part of receptivity? *Fertility and Sterility*.
- 14. Ülgen, E., Karacan, S., Gerlevik, U., Can, Ö., Bilguvar, K., Oktay, Y., Akyerli, C. B., & .... (2020). Mutations and copy number alterations in IDH wild-type glioblastomas are shaped by different oncogenic mechanisms. *Biomedicines*.
- 15. Ozduman, K., Ulgen, E., Karacan, S., Gerlevik, U., Can, O., Bilguvar, K., & .... (2020). Mutations and copy number alterations in diffuse gliomas are shaped by different mechanisms. *European Journal of Cancer*.
- 16. Ulgen, E., Ozisik, O., & Sezerman, O. (2019). pathfindR: An r package for comprehensive identification of enriched pathways in omics data through active subnetworks. *Frontiers in Genetics*.
- 17. Bastu, E., Demiral, I., Gunel, T., Ulgen, E., Gumusoglu, E., Hosseini, M., & .... (2019). Potential marker pathways in the endometrium that may cause recurrent implantation failure. *Reproductive Sciences*.
- 18. Ülgen, E., Bektaşoğlu, P., Sav, M., Can, Ö., Danyeli, A., Hızal, D., Pamir, M., & .... (2019). Meningiomas display a specific immunoexpression pattern in a rostrocaudal gradient: An analysis of 366 patients. *World Neurosurgery*.
- Ülgen, E., Can, Ö., Bilguvar, K., Oktay, Y., Akyerli, C., Danyeli, A., Yakıcıer, M., & .... (2019). Whole exome sequencing–based analysis to identify DNA damage repair deficiency as a major contributor to gliomagenesis in adult diffuse gliomas. *Journal of Neurosurgery*.
- 20. Sezerman, O., Ulgen, E., Seymen, N., & Durasi, I. (2019). Bioinformatics workflows for genomic variant discovery, interpretation and prioritization. *Bioinformatics Tools for Detection and Clinical Interpretation of Genomic*....
- 21. Ulgen, E., & Ozisik, O. (2019). pathfindR: An r package for comprehensive identification of enriched pathways in omics data through active subnetworks. Front genet 10: 858 59 dogan b, gumusoglu e, ulgen e .... *Genomics Inform*.
- 22. Akyerli, C., Yüksel, Ş., Can, Ö., Erson-Omay, E., Oktay, Y., Coşgun, E., & . . . (2018). Use of telomerase promoter mutations to mark specific molecular subsets with reciprocal clinical behavior in IDH mutant and IDH wild-type diffuse gliomas. *Journal of Neurosurgery*.
- 23. Ulgen, E., Ozisik, O., & Sezerman, O. (2018). pathfindR: An r package for pathway enrichment analysis utilizing active subnetworks. *BioRxiv*.
- 24. Bastu, E., Demiral, I., Ulgen, E., Erkan, M., Celik, S., Aydin, Y., Onem, A., & .... (2018). Lipidomic analysis reveals increased TXA2 presence in non-receptive endometrium of recurrent miscarriage and repeated implantation failure patients. *HUMAN REPRODUCTION*.
- 25. Dogan, M., Demiral, I., Akgun, E., Ulgen, E., Gurel, B., Sahin, B., Aytan, A., & . . . . (2018). Endometrial proteomic signature in recurrent implantation failure. *HUMAN REPRODUCTION*.
- 26. Demiral, I., Gumusoglu, E., Ulgen, E., Hosseini, M., Ozgor, B., Dogan, M., & .... (2018). Endometrial transcriptomic pathways analysis in recurrent miscarriages and unexplained infertility. *HUMAN REPRODUCTION*.
- 27. Ozduman, K., Ulgen, E., Can, O., Akyerli, C., & Pamir, M. (2018). Analysis of mutational processes in 23 adult hemispheric diffuse gliomas identifies DNA-damage repair deficiency as a major contributor to gliomagenesis. *JOURNAL OF NEUROSURGERY*.
- 28. Siva, A., Everest, E., Ülgen, E., UygunoÄŸlu, U., Tütüncü, M., Saip, S., & .... (2018). Identification of multiple sclerosis related pathways through genome-proteome correlations. *ACTRIMS Forum*.
- 29. Çağlayan, A., Sezer, R., Kaymakçalan, H., Ulgen, E., Yavuz, T., & .... (2017). ALPK3 gene mutation in a patient with congenital cardiomyopathy and dysmorphic features. *Molecular Case Studies*.
- 30. Ülgen, E., & Asar, Ö. (2017). Tekrarlı gözlem ve sağkalım verilerinin bileşik modellenmesi. *Türkiye Klinikleri Biyoistatistik*.

- 31. Demiral, I., Bastu, E., Gunel, T., Sezerman, U., Gumusoglu, E., Ulgen, E., & .... (2017). Endometrial gene expression in patients with recurrent implantation failure. *Fertility and Sterility*.
- 32. Bastu, E., Gunel, T., Sezerman, O., Demiral, I., Gumusoglu, E., Ulgen, E., & .... (2017). RAC1 signaling pathway is crucial for etiology of repeated implantation failure (RIF). *Fertility and Sterility*.
- 33. Oktay, Y., Ülgen, E., Can, Ö., Akyerli, C., Yüksel, Ş., Erdemgil, Y., Durası, İ., & . . . . (2016). IDH-mutant glioma specific association of rs55705857 located at 8q24. 21 involves MYC deregulation. *Scientific Reports*.
- 34. Per, H., Canpolat, M., Bayram, A., Ulgen, E., Baran, B., Kardas, F., Gumus, H., & .... (2015). Clinical, electrodiagnostic, and genetic features of tangier disease in an adolescent girl with presentation of peripheral neuropathy. *Neuropediatrics*.
- 35. Bayram, A., Per, H., Quon, J., Canpolat, M., Ülgen, E., Doğan, H., Gumus, H., & .... (2015). A rare case of congenital fibrosis of extraocular muscle type 1A due to KIF21A mutation with marcus gunn jaw-winking phenomenon. *European Journal of Paediatric Neurology*.

# References

Available upon request